<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Lang | /mili]]></title>
  <link href="http://slashmili.org/blog/categories/lang/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://slashmili.org/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-13T22:31:19+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://slashmili.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Milad Rastian]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elixir]]></title>
    <link href="http://slashmili.org/blog/2016/02/06/elixir/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-06T09:33:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://slashmili.org/blog/2016/02/06/elixir</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It was almost a year ago that I got introduced to <a href="http://elixir-lang.org">Elixir</a>.
I remember my first impression was yet another language on top of another one.
In addition running a software on <a href="http://www.erlang.org/">Erlang/OTP</a>, it&rsquo;s totally different beast
and I was a bit skeptical about it. However I gave it a chance and after a year,
I&rsquo;m totally happy with the time I spend and
I believe that everyone should take advantage of the language and the platform that is running on.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Why Elixir?</h2>

<h3>Eloquent &amp; Expressive</h3>

<p><code>elixir
urls = ["http://google.com", "http://trello.com"]
random_url = urls |&gt; Enum.shuffle |&gt; List.first
</code></p>

<p>Do I need to explain the code? Don&rsquo;t think so!
And if you have a bit of unix background this code should make sense to you.</p>

<blockquote><p><small>Yes, there is an easy way to get random item, the above code is just for making the point.</small></p></blockquote>

<p>BTW did I tell you Elixir is a functional programming language?
If you are not familiar with functional programming, it might take sometime to get to use
to that, after you un-learn your OOP skills, you&rsquo;ll find that every thing make sense in Elixir land.</p>

<h3>Mature Environment</h3>

<p>Elixir comes with tools that help you to develop and build your project:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://elixir-lang.org/docs/stable/mix/Mix.html">Mix</a> is a build tool to run your tasks.</li>
<li><a href="https://hex.pm/">Hex</a> is a package manager that is done right.</li>
<li><a href="http://elixir-lang.org/docs/stable/ex_unit/ExUnit.html">ExUnit</a> is your unit testing framework.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/elixir-lang/ex_doc">ExDoc</a> generates documentation for your Elixir projects.</li>
</ul>


<p>Also Elixir runs on <a href="https://www.erlang.org/">Erlang Virtual Machine(BEAM)</a> which has been <a href="https://www.quora.com/Which-companies-use-the-Erlang-language">around us</a> for quite some time.</p>

<h3>Metaprogramming</h3>

<p>Whenever I&rsquo;m learning a new language, after I get enough familiar with the language and it&rsquo;s syntax the first thing
I&rsquo;m looking for is how can I write a code that writes code for me!</p>

<p>The way that elixir does that is quite interesting.
Elixir&rsquo;s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abstract_syntax_tree">AST</a> can be represented by Elixir&rsquo;s own data
structures. Having the AST accessible by normal Elixir code lets you do very powerful
things because you can operate at the level typically reserved only for compilers and language designers.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say you want to humanize a mathematical equation, the interface and output should be like this:</p>

<p><code>elixir
iex &gt; Math.say 1 + 2
1 plus 2 is 3
3
iex &gt; Math.say 5 + 7
5 plus 7 is 12
12
</code></p>

<p>To achieve that we need to write a <code>macro</code> that matches with AST of <code>1 + 2</code>.
Thanks to Elixir&rsquo;s <code>quote</code> function it&rsquo;s easy to find out how it looks like:</p>

<p><code>elixir
iex &gt; quote do: 1 + 2
{:+, [context: Elixir, import: Kernel], [1, 2]}
</code></p>

<p>Now that we know how <code>1 + 2</code> is represented in Elixir&rsquo;s format we can write a <code>defmacro</code> that
matches with that data:</p>

<p>```elixir
defmodule Math do
  defmacro say({:+, _, [lhs, rhs]}) do</p>

<pre><code>quote do
  lhs = unquote lhs
  rhs = unquote rhs
  result = lhs + rhs
  IO.puts "#{lhs} plus #{rhs} is #{result}"
  result
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>You can read more about macros in
<a href="https://pragprog.com/book/cmelixir/metaprogramming-elixir">Metaprogramming Elixir</a> book.</p>

<blockquote><p><small>this example is from the same book</small></p></blockquote>

<p>I have to mention that
<a href="http://elixir-lang.org/docs/master/elixir/Kernel.html#if/2">if</a> and most of the Elixir&rsquo;s keywords
are implemented as a <code>macro</code>.</p>

<h3>Concurrent</h3>

<p>Having a concurrent system in Elixir is inevitable. In addition because the data
are immutable you don&rsquo;t need to worry about concurrent processes stepping on each others toes.
Elixir achieves that by running on top of BEAM.</p>

<p>How does it work? Let&rsquo;s say you want run a few queries and send the results back to the user</p>

<p><code>elixir
iex &gt; run_query = fn (query) -&gt;
  1000
  |&gt; :random.uniform
  |&gt; :timer.sleep
  IO.inspect "query #{query} executed"
end
</code></p>

<blockquote><p><small> Not all the queries finish in the same time, to simulate that we sleep random amount of time</small></p></blockquote>

<p>It would be nice to run independent queries concurrently, let&rsquo;s try it in <code>iex</code>:</p>

<p>```elixir
iex > spawn(fn &ndash;> run_query.(&lsquo;select * from users&rsquo;) end)</p>

<h1>PID&lt;0.132.0></h1>

<p>iex > spawn(fn &ndash;> run_query.(&lsquo;select * from reports&rsquo;) end)</p>

<h1>PID&lt;0.134.0></h1>

<p>&ldquo;query select * from users executed&rdquo;
&ldquo;query select * from reports executed&rdquo;
```</p>

<p>As you can see both queries executed concurrently.</p>

<p>You might ask how can I get back the results and use them in the main process? The answer is <em>Message Passing</em>.</p>

<p>```elixir
iex > caller = self
iex > spawn(fn &ndash;> send(caller, {:query_result, run_query.(&lsquo;select * from reports&rsquo;)}) end)</p>

<h1>PID&lt;0.138.0></h1>

<p>&ldquo;query select * from reports executed&rdquo;
iex > receive do</p>

<pre><code>{:query_result, result} -&gt; IO.inspect "result is #{result}"
end
</code></pre>

<p>&ldquo;result is query select * from reports executed&rdquo;
&ldquo;result is query select * from reports executed&rdquo;
```</p>

<p>The processes in Elixir(it&rsquo;s not same as unix processes) can talk to each other through message.
Each process has it&rsquo;s own mailbox and can process one item at a time.</p>

<h3>Distributed</h3>

<p>I save the best for last.</p>

<p>Erlang and its BEAM was implemented to be run in distributed environment.
You can easily connect two Erlang nodes together:</p>

<p>Node1:
<code>elixir
$ iex --sname node1
iex(node1@localhost)&gt;
</code></p>

<p>Node2:
<code>elixir
$ iex --sname node2
iex(node2@localhost)&gt; Node.connect(:"node1@localhost")
iex(node2@localhost)&gt; Node.list
[:"node1@localhost"]
</code></p>

<p>After the nodes recognize each other,
you can run any piece of code in any node in the cluster.</p>

<p>Node2:
```elixir
iex(node2@localhost)> Node.spawn(
  :&ldquo;node1@localhost&rdquo;,
  fn &ndash;> IO.puts &ldquo;This code ran from #{node}&rdquo; end)
This code ran from node1@localhost</p>

<h1>PID&lt;8771.79.0></h1>

<p>```</p>

<p>It looks simple, isn&rsquo;t it? To be fair, building distributed application requires
more thought but hey at least the language and its environment are in your side!</p>

<h2>My experience</h2>

<p>Well I said why I like Elixir but learning a new language is challenging and it&rsquo;s get
more complicated if it&rsquo;s running under different environment(Erlang/OTP).</p>

<ul>
<li>I did struggle with the idea of immutable data but after a while I got use to that.</li>
<li>Elixir has a few Hash/List like data structures and few times I got confused to choose between them. It&rsquo;s getting better since Elixir is depreciating <code>HashDict</code>.</li>
<li>Building a concurrent, fault-tolerant system under BEAM requires knowledge about OTP framework(<a href="https://www.manning.com/books/elixir-in-action">Elixir in Action</a> can help you a lot).</li>
<li>Even though Elixir code runs under the VM, the development cycle is fast! Mix and Hex are doing great job, the dependencies are downloaded and compiled very fast. I can fire up <code>iex</code> console or run <code>mix test</code> and quickly get the result back.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Where to start</h2>

<p>Are you interested? Spending most of my time reading Elixir/Erlang related book I can give you some suggestions</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://pragprog.com/book/elixir12/programming-elixir-1-2">Programming Elixir</a>
This book helps you to get familiar with the language and master it.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.manning.com/books/elixir-in-action">Elixir in Action</a>
You&rsquo;ve read <em>Programming Elixir</em> but still have lot of questions about using OTP? This book is for you.</li>
<li><a href="https://pragprog.com/book/phoenix/programming-phoenix">Programming Phoenix</a>
Are you ready to write your first app in Elixir? If it&rsquo;s a web app you can use Phoenix.</li>
<li><a href="https://pragprog.com/book/cmelixir/metaprogramming-elixir">Metaprogramming Elixir</a>
You&rsquo;ve built your first app in Phoenix but wondering how Phoenix does all of those tricks? It&rsquo;s time to level up and become master in Elixir Metaprogramming by reading this book.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
